Finding Aid for Edward Young papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward Young papers circa 1928-1940
Young, Edward, 1887-1964.
07182 Aa 2; UAs
Professor of civil engineering at the University of Michigan. Collection consists of 16mm film of activities at U-M's Cam p Davis in Wyoming with additional footage at Yellowstone National Park and Douglas Lake, Michigan.
16 film reels
1 folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donor No. 9050.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Edward Young was born July 11, 1887, in Longside, Ontario, Canada. He was admitted as a student to the University of Michigan in 1915 and graduated in 1921 with a B.S. in Civil Engineering. Edward worked as a construction engineer in Pennsylvania August 1918-June 1919 and as a teaching assistant in surveying at the University of Michigan in 1919 and 1920. After graduation, he was immediately hired as an Instructor in surveying, later as Instructor in Geodesy and surveying at the University of Michigan. He was promoted to assistant professor in 1927 and associate professor in 1947. Edward was acting director of the Camp Davis Summer session in 1938. He retired at the end of the academic year in 1957 and shortly after was granted emeritus status. He died in Ann Arbor on February 6, 1964.
Silent, 16 mm motion pictures, mainly of surveying and geological activities at Camp Davis, Wyoming, with additional footage at Yellowstone National Park and Douglas Lake, Michigan. All but one of the films are in black and white. In addition, there are five photographs of the annual Camp Davis Summer session participants for the years 1929-1933. The films were digitized in 2009. DVD versions are available for use in the reading and streaming files for selected films are available online.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Camp Davis (University of Michigan); Douglas Lake (Mich.); Surveying--Wyoming.; Surveying--Michigan.; Wyoming.; Yellowstone National Park.; Young, Edward, 1887-1964.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Photographs
  - Photos (Folder 1)
    (located at UAs)
- Motion Pictures
  - Camp Davis/Douglas Lake Pre-1929 Hydrographic Survey Training undated, 07182-1
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:07:00 @ 18fps.
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-1, flash
  - Camp Davis/Douglas Lake, Michigan 1928 1928, 07182-2
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:10:28 @ 18 fps
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-2, flash
  - Camp Davis 1929-Reel 1 1929, 07182-3
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:13:26 @ 18 fps
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-3, flash
  - Camp Davis 1929-Reel 2 1929, 07182-4
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:10:55 @ 18 fps
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-4, flash
  - Camp Davis 1930 (or 1931 ?)-Reel 1 circa 1930, 07182-5
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:13:33 @ 18 fps
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
  - Camp Davis 1931-Reel 2. Trip through Yellowstone 1931, 07182-6
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:09:44 @ 18 fps.
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-6, flash
  - Camp Davis 1934, 1934, 07182-7
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:14:40 @ 18 fps.
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-7, flash
  - Yellowstone and Camp Davis 1935, 1935, 07182-8
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:13:20 @ 18 fps.
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-8, flash
  - Camp Davis 1938/39-Overall Good of Camp, Surveying and Geology Students 1938, 07182-9
    - Original, 16mm film, color, pos, silent, 00:15:48 @ 18 fps.
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-9, flash
  - Camp Davis 1939, 1939, 07182-10
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:10 :55 @ 18 fps.
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-10, flash
  - Camp Davis (28) undated, 07182-11
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:08:11 @ 18 fps.
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-11, flash
  - Yellowstone 1930, 1930, 07182-12
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:16:22 @ 18 fps.
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-12, flash
  - Untitled (972) undated, 07182-13
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:15:40 @ 18 fps.
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-13, flash
  - Camp Davis (X) undated, 07182-14
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:11:11 @ 18 fps.
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-14, flash
  - Camp Davis (18 or 81) undated, 07182-15
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:14:15 @ 18fps.
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-15, flash
  - Camp Davis undated, 07182-16
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:05:31 @ 18fps
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-16, flash
  - Camp Davis 1931-Solar Obs. and Prairie Leveling 1931, 07182-17
    - Original, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:01:42 @ 18 fps
    - Use Copy, DVD (Box 10)
    - Streaming File: 07182-17, flash